Guide to the Mart Albert Howard Papers and Photographs of the Klondike 1897-1915
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Mart Albert Howard Papers and Photographs of the Klondike
1897-1915
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Cage 63
Howard, Mart Albert
7 containers. 3 linear feet of shelf space. 800 items.
Correspondence, diaries, financial and legal papers, photographs and lantern slides and other papers of Howard's experiences as a gold miner in the Klondike, 1898-1905.
Mart A. Howard (1855-1926) was a businessman at Webster, Massachusetts in 1897 when news of the Klondike gold strikes reached the United States. He left from home in October of that year, taking a train to Portland, then on to Seattle where he outfitted for a trip to Alaska. Leaving Seattle in January 1898, he traveled north via coastal steamer to Dyea, then across Chilkoot Pass and along inland waterways to his eventual destination at Dawson, Yukon Territory. In the fall of the same year, he returned to Seattle and purchased a shipment of supplies, which he retailed in the Klondike the following spring. Using the profits of this mercantile venture, he became a mine operator, purchasing interests in various mines on the creeks north of Dawson. He returned briefly to Massachusetts in 1900 after which he took his third trip to the Klondike, this time accompanied by his wife and son. Howard remained in Dawson until 1905, after which he returned to Massachusetts permanently. In later years he became a public lecturer on the Klondike gold rush.
The papers of Mart Albert Howard, 1855-1926, consists of the correspondence, diaries, bills and receipts, legal documents and photographs which Howard, a Webster, Massachusetts, businessman, retained from his experience as a gold miner in the Klondike gold rush of 1897. Approximately two thirds of the collection are photographs taken by Howard or purchased from other Alaskan and Canadian photographers. Most photographs are glass-mounted transparencies.
This collection is open for research use.
Mart Howard's son Louis, who was 14 at the time of his trip to the Klondike and who was later Dean Of Mining at Washington State University, saved his father's papers until his own death in 1944. His widow then preserved the papers until she deposited then with the WSU Library in 1958.
The Howard Papers were acquired by the Washington State University Library in 1958 from Howard's daughter in law, Mrs. Louis O. Howard.
A lengthy description of the papers in this collection may be found in Mary W. Avery, The Mart A. Howard Klondike Collection, Pacific Northwest Quarterly, 50 (1959) 53-62.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Howard, Mart Albert, 1855-1926 --Archives
Alaska--Pictorial works; Klondike River Valley (Yukon)--Gold discoveries -- Pictorial works
Mines and mineral resources--Yukon Territory--History--Sources; Steamboats -- Photographs
Photographs; Alaska; Mines and Mineral Resources
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Series 1: Diaries, letters, papers, records, souvenirs, clippings
  - Diaries of Mart Howard, 1897-1900; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters of Mart Howard to wife and son in Webster, Mass., 1897-1905; 120 items. (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Letters received by Mart Howard on business matters, 1902-1913; 30 items. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Invoices and account book for purchases of supplies from Seattle and Klondike firms, 1897-1905; 50 items. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Financial records of mining operations including profit and loss statement, "balance sheets" time books, 1898-1905; 40 items. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Contracts, license, writs, deeds and other legal documents (included is 1860 permit to drive cattle through Dudley, Mass., 1898-1905; 25 items. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Souvenirs and mementos of southeast Alaska, Klondike region, including theater bills, boat menus and letterheads, 1897-1905; 20 items: 5x8 postcards (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General information regarding the territory of Alaska. Interior Dept., 1914 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Report on reduction of area of homesteads in Alaska to 160 acres, Interior Dept., 1915 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mounted Newspaper clippings, re: Mart Howard; trial of George O'Brien at Dawson, Y.T., 1899-1905; 40 items. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Material for lectures on Klondike by Mart Howard, 1910; 25 items. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series 2: Photographs (Photoprints) of Klondike Gold Rush
  - 1. Panorama of Fairbanks, June 13, 1905 (Box Oversize)
  - 2-4. Dawson, Y.T. 70-0200, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 5. Episcopal Church and Hospital, Fairbanks (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 6. Footbridge, Fairbanks (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 7. Roll Call at the "N.C.C. Store" Fairbanks (liquor Wholesale), April 9, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 8. (Log) Jam formed above Cushman St. Bridge, Fairbanks, July 1, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 9. Pack Train Arriving with Gold Dust, Washington and Alaska Bank, Fairbanks. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 10. Removing Jam from above Cushman St. Bridge (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 11. Removing Jam from above Cushman St. Bridge. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 12. Below Bonanza (diggings) of Howard, Magaw and Collins (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 13. Sluicing on Checaco Hill, May 11, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 14. Below Bonanza, Howard, Magaw, and Collins Diggings (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 15. Below Bonanza, Howard, Magaw, and Collins (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 16. Panorama of Dawson City (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 17. No. 4 El Dorado, looking up Gold Hill (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 18. No. 6 Below on Bonanza (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 19. Midnight Scenic of Dawson, June 21, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 20. Hoisting Gold 1000 ft. to surface-winching machinery. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 21. Group of men on porch of building (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 22. Stores in Fairbanks (with M.A. Howard in scene) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 23. Top of tramway or ore chute (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 24. Our Klondike home, July 12, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 25. T.M. RR Train at the Junction between Fairbanks and Chema (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 26. Seattle waterfront, March 4, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 27. 1000 Ft. Underground Cripple Creek, Colorado (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 28. Mining Gold in Cripple Creek District (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 29. The Elkton Mine, Cripple Creek, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 30. National Hotel, Cripple Creek (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 31. Bennett Ave., Cripple Creek (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 32. Mary McKinney Mine Cripple Creek District (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 33. Portland Mine (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 34. Economic Mill, Cripple Creek District (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 35. Victor, Colorado (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 36. The Center of the Great Mining District, Cripple Creek Colorado. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 37. Adams Gulch (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 38. The Portland, Colorado’s Greatest Gold Mine (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 39. The Center of Cripple Creek Mining District (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 40. (Old Dominion?) Alaska or Yukon Mine Head, Sluice Box (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 41. Below Bonanza (Howard, Magaw, and Collins) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 42. Ice in Yukon River at Dawson, May 19, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 43. Ice Cakes at Forty-Mile, Yukon Territory, 15 feet thick, May 19, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 44. Log Jam-Fairbanks (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 45. Mart Howard en route to Klondike Gold Fields (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 46. Mart Howard en route to Klondike Gold Fields (Chilkoot Pass) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 47. Mart Howard en route to Klondike Gold Fields (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 48. Flood at Fairbanks, July 6, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 49. No. 7 Below Bonanza—(Sluice Box and people) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 50. Below Bonanza, Howard, Magaw and Collins (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 51. Howard, Magaw and Collins Mine (?) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 52. El Dorado (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 53. Midnight Street Scene—Dawson (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 54. Mining Scene on (Gold Sun?) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 55. Below Bonanza—Howard, Magaw, and Collins Mine (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 56. Fairbanks, Alaska, from across Chena river. oversize 70-0203, 70-0204., June 13, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 57. Military Post (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 58. General Store (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 59. Steamer Clifford Siftor in Miles Canyon (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 60. Enroute to Klondike Gold Fields (Chilkoot Pass) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 61. Shooting White Horse Rapids (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 62. S.S. Cutch in Port at Skagway (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series 3: Lantern Slides: Copy Negatives
  - #3 Enlarged Map of Chilkoot, Chilkat, and White Pass Routes, 70- 0207 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #4 Map of Klondike Mining District (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #6 Map of Klondike Gold Rush Area (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #10 Steamers Colombian and El Dorado racing 70-0208 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #11 Steamer El Dorado in ice 70-0209 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #13 Steamer Canadian 70-0210 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #14 Steamer John C. Barr 70-0211 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #15 Steamer White Horse 70-0212 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #26 Steamer (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #98 Second Avenue, dawson 70-0214 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #99 Front Street, Dawson 70-0215, July 5, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #101 Street in Dawson 70-0216 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #108 Administrative Building, Dawson 70-0217 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #127 Canadian Bank of Commerce (Dawson?) 70-218 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #143 (Front Street, Dawson?) Crowd scene 70-219 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #144 (Front Street, Dawson?) Crowd scene 70-220 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #185 Rocker Box 70-222 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #309 Scow dealers 70-0233 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - #313 A Yukon stove 70-224 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series 4: Lantern Slides
  - Maps
    - Northwest North America (Box 3, Slide 1-2)
    - Chilkoot, Chilkat and White Pass Routes (Box 3, Slide 3)
    - Klondike Mining District (Box 3, Slide 4-5)
    - Klondike Gold Rush Area (Box 3, Slide 6)
    - Utah, Colorado Area (Box 3, Slide 7)
  - Transport
    - Steamboats
      - Victorian (Box 3, Slide 8-9)
      - Colombian and Eldorado racing (Box 3, Slide 10)
      - Eldorado in ice (Box 3, Slide 11)
      - Canadian (Box 3, Slide 12-13)
      - John C. Barr at Hootalinqua, Y.T. (Box 3, Slide 14)
      - White Horse (Box 3, Slide 15)
      - Cutch in ice (Box 3, Slide 16)
      - Susie (Box 3, Slide 17)
      - Dolphin (Box 3, Slide 18)
      - Alki (Box 3, Slide 19)
      - Wharves (Box 3, Slide 20-21)
      - Steamboats and barges (Box 3, Slide 22)
      - Coastal steamer in ice (Box 3, Slide 23)
      - Crowd awaiting 2 steamers (Box 3, Slide 24)
      - (Steamboats) in winter quarters (Box 3, Slide 25)
      - Steamers (Box 3, Slide 26-27)
      - Roping a steamer through 5-finger rapids (Box 3, Slide 28)
      - Miners leaving Seattle on Ohio (Box 3, Slide 29)
      - On board steamer to Alaska (Box 3, Slide 30-32)
    - Boats
      - Boat landing at Dawson, Y.T. (Box 3, Slide 33)
      - Small Boats, some in sails (Box 3, Slide 34)
      - Canoes (Box 3, Slide 35)
    - Railroads
      - Train in deep snow (Box 3, Slide 36)
      - Locomotive with Snowplow (Box 3, Slide 37)
      - TMRR train (Box 3, Slide 38)
      - Track, trestlings, grades, bridges (Box 3, Slide 39-43)
    - Wagons
      - Teams and freight wagons (Box 3, Slide 44-47)
    - Sleds
      - Dog teams and sleds (Box 3, Slide 48-52)
      - Horse drawn sleds (Box 3, Slide 53-59)
      - Hand sled (Box 3, Slide 60)
    - Trails, Packing-In
      - Trail Depot (Box 3, Slide 61)
      - Packing over Chilkoot Pass (Box 3, Slide 62-65)
      - Trails (Box 3, Slide 66-71)
    - Pack Animals
      - Pack Mules (Box 3, Slide 72)
      - Pack Train with Shipment of gold (Box 3, Slide 73)
  - Cities, Settlements
    - Panoramas
      - Cordova (Box 4, Slide 74)
      - Dyea (Box 4, Slide 75)
      - Fairbanks (Box 4, Slide 76-77)
      - Forty-Mile (Box 4, Slide 78)
      - Grand Forks of Bonanza and Eldorado (Box 4, Slide 79-80)
      - Juneau (Box 4, Slide 81)
      - Ketchikan (Box 4, Slide 82)
      - Log Cabin, B.C. (Box 4, Slide 83)
      - Moosehide, Y.T. (Box 4, Slide 84)
      - Port Townsend, WA (Box 4, Slide 85)
      - Seattle (Box 4, Slide 86)
      - Skagway (Box 4, Slide 87)
      - Stewart, Y.T. (Box 4, Slide 88)
      - Vancouver, B.C. (Box 4, Slide 89)
      - Victoria, B.C. (Box 4, Slide 90)
      - Wrangel (Box 4, Slide 91)
      - Unidentified cities (Box 4, Slide 92-97)
    - Streets
      - Dawson, Y.T. (Box 4, Slide 98-101)
      - Skagway (Box 4, Slide 102-103)
      - Sitka (Box 4, Slide 104)
      - Flooded village (Box 4, Slide 105)
      - Unidentified (Box 4, Slide 106)
    - Buildings
      - Administrative Building, Dawson (Box 4, Slide 107-108)
      - Fire Station, Dawson (Box 4, Slide 109)
      - Church and Hospital (Box 4, Slide 110-111)
      - Parliament, Victoria (Box 4, Slide 112)
      - Parliament, Ottawa (Box 4, Slide 113)
      - Empress Hotel, Victoria (Box 4, Slide 114)
      - San Francisco Post Office (Box 4, Slide 115)
      - GAR post, Worcester, Mass. (Box 4, Slide 116)
      - The Royal Fuel Factory (Box 4, Slide 117)
      - Fort Selkirk buildings (Box 4, Slide 118)
      - White Horse Depot (?) (Box 4, Slide 119)
      - Stores (Box 4, Slide 120)
      - Canadian Pacific RR Offices, Victoria (Box 4, Slide 121)
      - Canadian Development Company Trading Post (Box 4, Slide 122)
      - Nugget Lunch House (Box 4, Slide 123)
      - Interior of Russian Orthodox Church (Box 4, Slide 124)
      - Cabin Fever (Box 4, Slide 125)
      - Canneries at Petersburg, Alaska (Box 4, Slide 126)
      - Canadian Bank of Commerce (Box 4, Slide 127)
      - Unidentified public buildings and dwellings (Box 4, Slide 128-132)
      - Encampments on Lakes Bennett and Lindeman (Box 4, Slide 133-135)
      - Camps (Box 4, Slide 136-140)
      - Tennis Courts at Valdez (Box 4, Slide 141)
    - Encampment and City Scenes
      - Scenes around Dawson (Box 5, Slide 142-144)
      - Crowds in Streets (Box 5, Slide 145-147)
      - Log Jam behind footbridge in Fairbanks (Box 5, Slide 148-150)
  - Mining
    - Panoramas
      - Adams Gulch (Box 5, Slide 151-152)
      - Bonanza (Box 5, Slide 153-157)
      - Chechaco Hill (Box 5, Slide 158-159)
      - Eldorado (Box 5, Slide 160-161)
      - Unidentified (Box 5, Slide 162-168)
    - Dredging
      - On Bonanza (Box 5, Slide 169-171)
      - On Lower Hunker Creek (Box 5, Slide 172)
      - On Klondike River (Box 5, Slide 173-174)
    - Tramway
      - The Fassbender and May Tramway (Box 5, Slide 175-180)
      - The Fassbender and May Tramway (Box 6, Slide 181-183)
    - Hand Tools and Simple Mining Operations
      - Group with rocker and pans (Box 6, Slide 184)
      - Rockers (Box 6, Slide 185-188)
      - A Long Tom (Box 6, Slide 189)
      - Panning (Box 6, Slide 190)
      - Hand winches or windlasses (Box 6, Slide 191-193)
      - Hydraulic mining (Box 6, Slide 194-195)
      - Sluices (Box 6, Slide 196-202)
    - Mine Interiors
      - Cage (Box 6, Slide 203)
      - Driving steam points (Box 6, Slide 204)
      - Digging by Hand (Box 6, Slide 205)
      - Timberwork (Box 6, Slide 206-207)
    - Steam Equipment
      - Steam pipes (Box 6, Slide 208-210)
      - Steam hoists at mine heads (Box 6, Slide 211-215)
      - Ore Cars (Box 6, Slide 216-218)
      - Ore Stackers (Box 6, Slide 219-220)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Slide 221-225)
      - Assay Labs (Box 6, Slide 226-227)
      - Surface Mining, probably in Southwest United States (Box 6, Slide 228-239)
    - Landscapes
      - Rivers or Inlets (Box 7, Slide 240-251)
      - 5-Finger Rapids (Box 7, Slide 252-254)
      - Glaciers (Box 7, Slide 255-256)
      - Waterfalls (Box 7, Slide 257-259)
      - Forest (Box 7, Slide 260-261)
      - Desert (Box 7, Slide 262-263)
      - Gold Hill (Box 7, Slide 264)
  - Portraits
    - Individual and dual
      - Robert Henderson (Box 7, Slide 265)
      - George Carmack (Box 7, Slide 266)
      - Unidentified, including miners, Indians, laborers (Box 7, Slide 267-278)
    - Groups
      - Violet Basketball Team (Box 7, Slide 279)
      - Group at Rapids (Box 7, Slide 280)
      - Midnight Dome, June 21 (Box 7, Slide 281)
      - School Children (Box 7, Slide 282)
      - Border Officials (Box 7, Slide 283)
      - Groups and crowds (Box 7, Slide 284-291)
      - Novelty Portraits, including women panning, miner doing laundry, etc. (Box 7, Slide 292-295)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Building a road (Box 7, Slide 296)
    - Totem Poles (Box 7, Slide 297)
    - Shooting a rapid (Box 7, Slide 298)
    - Firewood pile (Box 7, Slide 299)
    - On a sandbar (Box 7, Slide 300)
    - Log Pile (Box 7, Slide 301)
    - A saw pit (Box 7, Slide 302)
    - Color photos of vegetation, mostly flowers (Box 7, Slide 303-306)
    - 1/2 Million Dollars worth of gold (Box 7, Slide 307)
    - A typical Malumute dog (Box 7, Slide 308)
    - Scow dealers (peddlers) (Box 7, Slide 309)
    - Milk Stand (Box 7, Slide 310)
    - Milk Cows (Box 7, Slide 311)
    - Shipment of Gold (Box 7, Slide 312)
    - A Yukon Stove (Box 7, Slide 313)
    - 25,000 Salmon at Anacortes, WA (Box 7, Slide 314)
    - Ice Cakes from Yukon River (Box 7, Slide 315)
    - United States Flag (Box 7, Slide 316)
    - United States and Imperial Flags (Box 7, Slide 317)
    - Machinery Fairbanks, Morse, and Company stamp and amalgamation mill (Box 7, Slide 318-326)
    - Steel Crystallography (Box 7, Slide 327-366)
    - X-Ray of a key and coin (Box 7, Slide 367)
    - Newspapers: Dawson, Yukon Territory; Skagway, Alaska., 1899-1905; 7 items. (Box Oversize)